Guide to the Robert Kaplan Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Kaplan papers
1918-1971
1945-1959
MS 879
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The collection consists of correspondence, research materials and unpublished writings of Robert Kaplan. The research materials and writings document John L. Lewis, the UMWA Welfare and Retirement Fund, and Josephine Roche, retirement fund director.
Kaplan, Robert
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Grace Kaplan, 1978.
Associated Materials
Forms part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Kaplan was the research director for the United Mine Workers Union of America (UMWA) from 1942 to 1967. He also served as the archivist in charge of documenting American labor leader John L. Lewis' term as president of the UMWA. As research director, Kaplan often contributed commentaries on economics and labor relations to the UMWA Journal.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, research materials and unpublished writings of Robert Kaplan. The research materials and writings document John L. Lewis, the UMWA Welfare and Retirement Fund, and Josephine Roche, retirement fund director.
Coal miners -- Labor unions; Coal miners -- United States; Industrial hygiene; Labor union welfare funds; Medicine; Public health; Authors; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Kaplan, Robert; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969; Roche, Josephine A. (Josephine Aspinwall), 1886-1976; United Mine Workers of America
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1943-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Research materials
    - John L. Lewis
      - Correspondence, 1946-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Memoranda and notices, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Photographs
        - General, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 6)
        - Portraits, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Senate Subcommittee on Labor and Public Welfare hearing, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 9)
      - Speeches and statements
        - General, 1920-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 15)
        - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Josephine Roche
      - Correspondence, 1959-1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Photographs, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Testimonies and statements, 1938-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Wage Earning Women and Girls in Baltimore [monograph], by Josephine Roche, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - UMWA Welfare and Retirement Fund
      - Manuscripts
        - "Causes of Conflict Between the UMWA Retirement Fund and Organized Medicine," by Peter Rich, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - "The Medical, Health and Hospital Service of the Welfare and Retirement Fund of the UMWA," by M. L. Ingar, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 22)
        - "The Healing Chain: How the Miners Created a New Pattern of Medical Care," by Alfred Deutsch, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 23 - 24)
      - Photographs
        - Disabled mine workers, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Centralia Mine disaster [for retirement fund pamphlet], 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Printed matter, 1930-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Writings
    - UMWA Journal, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Manuscripts
      - "A Better Life For American Mine Workers", undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - "Credit and Capital", undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - "My Twenty-Five Years with John L. Lewis", undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - "Progress and Plenty", undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - "The United Mine Workers Welfare and Retirement Fund: Its Background and History", undated (Box 3, Folder 33)